<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-ietf-babel-yang-model-06" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Babel YANG model">YANG Data Model for Babel</title>

    <author fullname="Mahesh Jethanandani" initials="M.J."
            surname="Jethanandani">
      <organization>Kloud Services</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city/>

          <code/>

          <region>California</region>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>mjethanandani@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Barbara Stark" initials="B.S." surname="Stark">
      <organization>AT&amp;T</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Atlanta</city>

          <region>GA</region>

          <code/>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <phone/>

        <facsimile/>

        <email>barbara.stark@att.com</email>

        <uri/>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="28" month="June" year="2020"/>

    <area>Routing Area</area>

    <workgroup>Babel Working Group</workgroup>

    <keyword>babel</keyword>

    <keyword>YANG</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document defines a data model for the Babel routing protocol.
      The data model is defined using the YANG data modeling language.</t>
    </abstract>

    <note title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119">BCP 14</xref><xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only
      when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </note>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t/>

      <t>This document defines a data model for the Babel routing protocol
      <xref target="I-D.ietf-babel-rfc6126bis"/>. The data model is defined
      using <xref target="RFC7950">YANG 1.1 </xref> data modeling language and
      is <xref target="RFC8342">Network Management Datastore Architecture
      (NDMA)</xref> compatible. It is based on the <xref
      target="I-D.ietf-babel-information-model">Babel Information Model
      </xref>.</t>

      <section title="Note to RFC Editor">
        <t>Artwork in this document contains shorthand references to drafts in
        progress. Please apply the following replacements and remove this note
        before publication.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>"XXXX" --&gt; the assigned RFC value for this draft both in
            this draft and in the YANG models under the revision
            statement.</t>

            <t>"ZZZZ" --&gt; the assigned RFC value for <xref
            target="I-D.ietf-babel-information-model">Babel Information Model
            </xref></t>

            <t>Revision date in model, in the format YYYY-MM-DD needs to get
            updated with the date the draft gets approved. The date also needs
            to get reflected on the line with &lt;CODE BEGINS&gt;.</t>
          </list></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Tree Diagram Annotations">
        <t>For a reference to the annotations used in tree diagrams included
        in this draft, please see <xref target="RFC8340">YANG Tree
        Diagrams</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Babel Module">
      <t>This document defines a <xref target="RFC7950">YANG 1.1</xref> data
      model for the configuration and management of Babel. The YANG module is
      based on the <xref target="I-D.ietf-babel-information-model">Babel
      Information Model</xref>.</t>

      <section title="Information Model">
        <t>There are a few things that should be noted between the Babel
        Information Model and this data module. The information model mandates
        the definition of some of the attributes, e.g.
        babel-implementation-version or the babel-self-router-id. These
        attributes are marked a read-only objects in the information module as
        well as in this data module. However, there is no way in the data
        module to mandate that a read-only attribute be present. It is up to
        the implementation of this data module to make sure that the
        attributes that are marked read-only and are mandatory are indeed
        present.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="Tree Diagram">
        <t>The following diagram illustrates a top level hierarchy of the
        model. In addition to information like the version number implemented
        by this device, the model contains subtrees on constants, interfaces,
        routes and security.</t>

        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-babel@YYYY-MM-DD-abridged-tree.txt)
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>

        <t>The interfaces subtree describes attributes such as interface
        object that is being referenced, the type of link as enumerated by
        metric-algorithm and split-horizon and whether the interface is
        enabled or not.</t>

        <t>The constants subtree describes the UDP port used for sending and
        receiving Babel messages, and the multicast group used to send and
        receive announcements on IPv6.</t>

        <t>The routes subtree describes objects such as the prefix for which
        the route is advertised, a reference to the neighboring route, and
        next-hop address.</t>

        <t>Finally, for security two subtree are defined to contain MAC keys
        and DTLS certificates. The mac subtree contains keys used with the MAC
        security mechanism. The boolean flag default-apply indicates whether
        the set of MAC keys is automatically applied to new interfaces. The
        dtls subtree contains certificates used with DTLS security mechanism.
        Similar to the MAC mechanism, the boolean flag default-apply indicates
        whether the set of DTLS certificates is automatically applied to new
        interfaces.</t>
      </section>

      <section title="YANG Module">
        <t>This YANG module augments the <xref target="RFC8349">YANG Routing
        Management</xref> module to provide a common framework for all routing
        subsystems. By augmenting the module it provides a common building
        block for routes, and Routing Information Bases (RIBs). It also has a
        reference to an interface defined by <xref target="RFC8343">A YANG
        Data Model for Interface Management</xref>.</t>

        <t>A router running Babel routing protocol can determine the
        parameters it needs to use for an interface based on the interface
        name. For example, it can detect that eth0 is a wired interface, and
        that wlan0 is a wireless interface. This is not true for a tunnel
        interface, where the link parameters need to be configured
        explicitly.</t>

        <t>For a wired interface, it will assume '2-out-of-3'
        'metric-algorithm', and 'split-horizon' set to true. On other hand,
        for a wireless interface it will assume 'etx' 'metric-algorithm', and
        'split-horizon' set to false. However, if the wired link is connected
        to a wireless radio, the values can be overriden by setting
        'metric-algorithm' to 'etx', and 'split-horizon' to false. Similarly,
        an interface that is a metered 3G link, and used for fallback
        connectivity needs much higher default time constants, e.g.
        'mcast-hello-interval', and 'update-interval', in order to avoid
        carrying control traffic as much as possible.</t>

        <t>In addition to the modules used above, this module imports
        definitions from <xref target="RFC6991">Common YANG Data Types</xref>,
        and references <xref target="RFC2104">HMAC: Keyed-Hashing for Message
        Authentication</xref>, <xref target="RFC4868">Using HMAC-SHA-256,
        HMAC-SHA-384, and HMAC-SHA-512</xref>, <xref target="RFC6347">Datagram
        Transport Layer Security Version 1.2</xref>, <xref
        target="RFC7693">The Blake2 Cryptographic Hash and Message
        Authentication Code (MAC)</xref>, <xref
        target="I-D.ietf-babel-information-model">Babel Information
        Model</xref>, and <xref target="I-D.ietf-babel-rfc6126bis">The Babel
        Routing Protocol</xref>.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
<CODE BEGINS> file "ietf-babel@YYYY-MM-DD.yang"

INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/ietf-babel@YYYY-MM-DD.yang)

<CODE ENDS>]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document registers one URIs and one YANG module.</t>

      <section title="URI Registrations">
        <t>URI: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-babel</t>
      </section>

      <section title="YANG Module Name Registration">
        <t>This document registers one YANG module in the YANG Module Names
        registry <xref target="RFC6020">YANG</xref>.</t>

        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[Name:ietf-babel
Namespace: urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-babel
prefix: babel
reference: RFC XXXX ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The YANG module specified in this document defines a schema for data
      that is designed to be accessed via network management protocol such as
      <xref target="RFC6241">NETCONF</xref> or <xref
      target="RFC8040">RESTCONF</xref>. The lowest NETCONF layer is the secure
      transport layer and the mandatory-to-implement secure transport is <xref
      target="RFC6242">SSH</xref>. The lowest RESTCONF layer is HTTPS, and the
      mandatory-to-implement secure transport is <xref
      target="RFC8446">TLS</xref>.</t>

      <t>The NETCONF Access Control Model (<xref target="RFC8341">NACM</xref>)
      provides the means to restrict access for particular NETCONF users to a
      pre-configured subset of all available NETCONF protocol operations and
      content.</t>

      <t>There are a number of data nodes defined in the YANG module which are
      writable/created/deleted (i.e., config true, which is the default).
      These data nodes may be considered sensitive or vulnerable in some
      network environments. Write operations (e.g., &lt;edit-config&gt;) to
      these data nodes without proper protection can have a negative effect on
      network operations.These are the subtrees and data nodes and their
      sensitivity/vulnerability from a config true perspective:</t>

      <t>babel: This container includes an "enable" parameter that can be used
      to enable or disable use of Babel on a router</t>

      <t>babel/constants: This container includes configuration parameters
      that can prevent reachability if misconfigured.</t>

      <t>babel/interfaces: This leaf-list has configuration parameters that
      can enable/disable security mechanisms and change performance
      characteristics of the Babel protocol.</t>

      <t>babel/hmac and babel/dtls: These contain security credentials that
      influence whether packets are trusted.</t>

      <t>Some of the readable data or config false nodes in this YANG module
      may be considered sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments.
      It is thus important to control read access (e.g., via get, get-config,
      or notification) to these data nodes. These are the subtrees and data
      nodes and their sensitivity/vulnerability from a config false
      perpective:</t>

      <t>babel: Access to the information in the various nodes can disclose
      the network topology. Additionally, the routes used by a network device
      may be used to mount a subsequent attack on traffic traversing the
      network device.</t>

      <t>babel/hmac and babel/dtls: These contain security credentials,
      include private credentials of the router.</t>

      <t>Some of the RPC operations in this YANG module may be considered
      sensitive or vulnerable in some network environments. It is thus
      important to control access to these operations. These are the
      operations and their sensitivity/vulnerability from a RPC operation
      perspective:</t>

      <t>babel/hmac/hmac/keys/test and babel/dtls/certs/test: These can be
      used in a brute force attack to identify the credentials being used to
      secure the Babel protocol.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Juliusz Chroboczek provided most of the example configurations for
      babel that are shown in the Appendix.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.4868'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6347'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.6991'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7950"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8343'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8349'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-babel-rfc6126bis"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2104'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6020"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6241"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6242"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7693'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8040"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8340"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8341"?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.8342'?>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8446"?>

      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.ietf-babel-information-model"?>
    </references>

    <section title="An Appendix">
      <t>This section is devoted to examples that demonstrate how Babel can be
      configured.</t>

      <section title="Statistics Gathering Enabled">
        <t>In this example, interface eth0 is being configured for routing
        protocol Babel, and statistics gathering is enabled. For security,
        HMAC-SHA256 is supported. Every sent Babel packets is signed with the
        key value provided, and every received Babel packet is verified with
        the same key value.<figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/example-babel-configuration-2.3.xml)
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Automatic Detection of Properties">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/example-babel-configuration-2.4.xml)
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Override Default Properties">
        <t><figure>
            <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/example-babel-configuration-2.5.xml)
]]></artwork>
          </figure></t>
      </section>

      <section title="Configuring other Properties">
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
INSERT_TEXT_FROM_FILE(../src/yang/example-babel-configuration-2.6.xml)
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
